Finding Aid for Salling, Hanson, and Company Records, 1881-1928
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Salling, Hanson, and Company records
1881-1928
Salling, Hanson, and Company (Grayling, Mich.)
85501 BB.2 Bb.2 2
The Salling, Hanson and Company Records are the business records of the lumber company Salling, Hanson and Company based in Grayling Michigan from 1881-1928. The records include financial data, annual reports, daily activity information as well as some records from other Grayling businesses.
4 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
44 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the company through John Brunn (Donor no. 3167 ).
The collection is open to research.
The Salling, Hanson and Company limber firm dominated the early economic life of Grayling, Michigan, and contributed greatly to the growth of the settlement. Salling, Hanson and Company was founded in 1878 by three Danish immigrants, Rasmus Hanson, Nels Michelson, and Ernest N. Salling. During nearly 50 years of operation, this company was a leading harvester of Michigan white pine. The business records of Salling, Hanson and Company represent a later stage of Michigan's lumbering industry. Although the company continued some operations until 1927, its most active phase of lumbering ended around 1912.
The Salling and Hanson records on microfilm begin with a series of ledger books, complete from 1881 to 1923, except for one volume which was missing. All of the company's financial transactions were transferred to the ledgers (which are arranged by accounts), making them the most complete records of company business. The journals and lumber journals (arranged chronologically) provide records of daily operations. Since these transactions were eventually recorded in the ledgers, only sample years of the journals and lumber journals were preserved. For both series, all records of even numbered years were microfilmed, including records for 1881, the earliest year for which Salling, Hanson records exist. The lumber journals may be of particular interest, since they indicate the amounts of various types of lumber produced and sold. An entire series of time books (1891-1907) was filmed, giving payroll accounts of Salling, Hanson employees. One petty accounts ledger (1917-1927) and one tax record book (1881-1891) complete the Selling, Hanson Company microfilm edition. Records preserved in the original form include 5 index volumes for the time books, trial balances, records of total lumber shipped, and annual reports of two subsidiary companies. In addition, two color-coded surveyor's books and three volumes of daily operations records (containing the only narrative material in the collection) have been preserved in the original.
More than half of the Salling, Hanson records were discarded. In addition to alternate years of the journals and lumber journals, several series of records were entirely discarded. Day books and cash books were discarded because information recorded in them was duplicated in the journals and ledgers. Merchandise ledgers and cash books for the Salling, Hanson Company store were discarded, along with lumber order books and a few miscellaneous volumes.
The Salling, Hanson microfilm series concludes with records of several companies with which Rasmus Hanson was affiliated. Hanson Lumber Company records (1901-1907) consist of one ledger and one journal. R. Hanson and Sons records (1909-1912) consist of a record of cars received. Hanson Land Company records (1914-1927) consist of ledgers, journals, and log records. Grayling Box Company records (1918-1943) consist of journals, sales journals, and payroll books. Finally, Grayling Hotel records (1916-1936) consist of ledger and journal books.
Subjects:
Business records.; Grayling Box Company.; Grayling Hotel.; Hanson Land Company (Grayling, Mich.); Hotels--Michigan--Grayling.; Land use--Michigan.; Logging--Michigan--Grayling.; Lumbering--Michigan--Grayling.
- Miscellaneous Records
  - Record of daily operations, 1896-1901; 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Surveyors record and field book of Rasmus Hanson, 1892; 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - Indexes to time books, 5 volumes (Box 2)
  - Trial balances, 1914-1917; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - R. Hanson and Sons Annual Report for 1921, 1 folders (Box 2)
  - Hanson Land and Lumber Company Annual Report (Box 2)
    - 1922, 1 folders (Box 2)
    - 1923, 1 folders (Box 2)
  - Record of total lumber shipped, 1889-1903; 1 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1 folders (Box 2)
  - Plat book (Volume BB.2)
- Ledgers, 1881-1923
  - July 1881-May 1885, 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 1)
  - May 1885-February 1888, 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - June 1889-November 1891, 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 3)
  - December 1891-March 1893, 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 4)
  - April 1893-September 1894, 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 5)
  - September 1894-January 1896, 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 6)
  - February 1896-April 1897, 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 7)
  - May 1897-December 1899, 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 8)
  - January 1900-April 1901, 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 9)
  - May 1901-June 1902, 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 10)
  - July 1902-October 1903, 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 11)
  - November 1903-February 1905, 1 volumes (Reel 12)
  - March 1905-March 1907, 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 13)
  - April 1907-August 1910, 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 14)
  - September 1910-April 1912, 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 15)
  - May 1912-March 1916, 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 16)
  - April 1916-October 1920, 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 17)
  - November 1920-December 1923, 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 18)
- Petty Accounts, 1917-1927
  - August 1917-October 1927, 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 18)
- Journals, 1881-1920
  - July-December 1881 (Box 3, Reel 18)
  - 1882, 1884; 1886; 1888; 4 volumes (Box 3, Reel 19)
  - 1890, 1892; 1894; 3 volumes (Box 3, Reel 20)
  - 1896, 1898; 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 21)
  - 1900, 1902; 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 22)
  - 1904, 1906; 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 23)
  - 1908, 1910; 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 24)
  - 1912, 1914; 1916; 3 volumes (Box 3, Reel 25)
  - 1918, 1920; 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 26)
- Lumber Journals, 1881-1928
  - 1881, 1882; 1886; 1888; 4 volumes (Box 3, Reel 26)
  - 1890, 1892; 1894; 3 volumes (Box 3, Reel 27)
  - 1896, 1898; 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 28)
  - 1900, 1902; 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 29)
  - 1904, 1906; 3 volumes (Box 3, Reel 30)
  - 1910, 1912; 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 31)
  - 1914, 1916; 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 32)
  - 1918, 1920; 1922; 3 volumes (Box 3, Reel 33)
  - 1924, 1926; 1928; 3 volumes (Box 3, Reel 34)
- Time Books, 1891-1907
  - January 1891-April 1892, 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 34)
  - May 1892-January 1895, 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 35)
  - February 1895-December 1897, 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 36)
  - January 1898-November 1900, 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 37)
  - December 1900-August 1903, 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 38)
  - September 1903-December 1905, 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 39)
  - January 1906-January 1907, 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 40)
- Tax Record Book, 1881-1891
  - 1881-1891, 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 40)
- Hanson Company Records, 1901-1927
  - Hanson Lumber Company Ledger, 1901-November 1903; 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 40)
  - Hanson Lumber Company Journal, July 1901-January 1907; 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 41)
  - R. Hanson and Sons Record of cars received, January 1909-March 1912; 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 41)
  - Hanson Land Company Record of logs lumbered and shipped, 1915-June 1916; 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 41)
  - Hanson Land Company Ledger, November 1914-June 1925; 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 41)
  - Hanson Land Company Journal, November 1914-October 1927; 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 42)
  - Hanson Land Company Log Record, January 1915-April 1918; 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 42)
- Grayling Box Company Records, 1924-1935
  - Grayling Box Company Journal, June 1924-November 1928; 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 42)
  - Grayling Box Company Journal, December 1928-December 1943; 2 volumes (Box 3, Reel 43)
  - Grayling Box Company Sales Journal, July 1918-November 1935; 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 43)
  - Grayling Box Company Payroll Book, January 1923-December 1927; 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 43)
  - Grayling Box Company Payroll Book, January 1931-December 1935; 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 44)
- Grayling Hotel Records
  - Grayling Hotel Ledger, April 1916-July 1936; 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 44)
  - Grayling Hotel Journal, April 1916-July 1936; 1 volumes (Box 3, Reel 44)
- Negative Microfilm (Box 4)